# **MELVIN TEJADA**

Al Portfolio: https://bit.ly/melvintejada

Email: tejada.melvin@gmail.com

LinkedIn: <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/melvin-tejada">https://linkedin.com/in/melvin-tejada</a>

Mobile: 202-754-1172

Tech strategy leader with a Master's in Industrial and Organizational Psychology from Harvard and 15+ years driving HR systems, workforce analytics, and enterprise IT programs. Trusted partner to CHROs and CFOs, aligning digital platforms with talent strategy, employee experience, and business goals.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Independent Consultant | Technical Program & Strategy Advisor

Jan 2024 – Present

- Strategic Advisory: Advise C-suite leaders on org. transformation, AI strategy, and executive comms.
- **Operational Excellence:** Designed frameworks to optimize business operations and governance and coached technology leaders on executive decision-making and high-impact strategic planning
- Human-Centered Tech Strategy: Completed Harvard's Master's in Industrial and Organizational
   Psychology + advanced AI/ML skills, deepening the ability to align HR priorities with technical strategy

### Amazon | Principal Program Manager - AWS Cybersecurity

2022 - 2024

- **Strategic Planning:** Developed and executed a long-term cybersecurity vision, aligning dynamic enterprise-wide technology initiatives and KPIs with cybersecurity staffing and budget resources
- **AI-Driven Product Management:** Led a global AI-powered vulnerability management platform strategy and roadmap, deploying machine learning models to detect enterprise security threats at scale
- Executive Communications: Led a program that directly briefed the AWS CEO every two months, providing insights on the global security posture and risk landscape of 50M global operating hosts
- **Cross-Functional Leadership:** Partnered with engineering, finance, and compliance teams to scale security automation and oversee program implementation; founded a Community of Practice (CoP) for product and program managers, mentoring emerging leaders in cybersecurity and AI strategy

#### McDonald's | Director of Strategic Alignment and Chief of Staff to Global CFO

2021 - 2022

- HR Systems Strategy & People Analytics: Led the development of AI-powered HR dashboards using for succession planning and talent strategy, expanding leadership pipeline by 175% (8 to 22 execs.)
- **Global Experience Platform:** Architected a global data solutions platform enabling analytics and simulation models for pricing, real estate, and marketing; impacted 7 million customers in 10 countries

#### Capital One | Senior Manager, People Tech. and Cloud Governance - Cyber Engineering

2018 – 2021

- **Business Operations:** Led AWS cyber engineering cloud spend governance, developing AI-driven cost models and budget forecasts aligned with technical requirements to optimize cloud spending
- Performance Management Automation: Delivered HR performance analytics solutions through KPI
  dashboards and automated reporting; partnered with PeopleOps and executive leadership to inform
  budgeting, talent investment, and training approvals for 250 technology associates

#### Georgetown University | Chief Administrative Officer for Technology & HR Systems

2016 – 2018

- **Strategic Leadership & Governance:** Led the oversight of technology operations, governance, financial strategy, and compliance programs for a campus community of 30,000 students, faculty, and staff across four global locations. Drove alignment between university-wide goals and technology integration
- HR Technology Modernization: Managed a \$30M Al-powered infrastructure modernization initiative
  with Verizon; Directed digital transformation for HR and administrative services by deploying scalable
  workflows in Workday and Canvas; improved global employee self-service

- Cross-Functional Program Ownership & Execution: Managed multiple high-impact technical programs,
  e.g., telecom billing and computer replacement cycles for over 6k employees. Ensured seamless
  deployment of enterprise systems, driving improved productivity and user adoption
- **Vendor Negotiations & Budget Management:** Negotiated major vendor contracts, resulting in a \$6 million deficit reduction, closing my first year with a \$1M surplus, while expanding tech programs
- **HR & Organizational Leadership:** Oversaw department-wide HR operations for 250+ staff including talent strategy, performance management, and compliance in support of strategic workforce planning

# Chicago Transit Authority (CTA) | Chief of Staff & Modernization Lead – Enterprise Security 2014 – 2016

- **Risk Intelligence Program Development:** Designed and implemented a data-driven risk intelligence program ranking all CTA routes based on city-wide collision data, enabling real-time safety interventions
- **Budget & Vendor Management:** Managed \$1.4 billion in funding, overseeing contract negotiations and vendor performance for security technology, transit safety programs, and risk assessment tools
- **Public Safety & Critical Infrastructure Security:** Led enterprise-wide security initiatives to mitigate risks across CTA's system, protecting 1.6 million daily riders from cyber, physical, and operational threats
- **Security & Law Enforcement Operations:** Partnered with law enforcement agencies on criminal transit system incidents. Conducted security audits and employee investigations and terminations

#### U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS) | Technical Program Manager, TS-SCI 2009 – 2014

TSA: Transportation Security Administration - Special Assistant to the Director and Senior Desk Officer

- **Embassy & Diplomatic Engagements:** Conducted security policy negotiations across five U.S. embassies, strengthening bilateral and multilateral security agreements with global partners
- Western Hemisphere and Asia Pacific: Traveled abroad with agency leadership; led negotiations on security, risk, and enforcement; coordinated classified missions with diplomatic and security agencies

CISA: Cybersecurity & Infrastructure Security Agency – Cyber Intelligence Technical Program Lead (former NPPD)

 National Cyber Risk & Intelligence: Owned a high-profile portfolio of cybersecurity critical infrastructure programs, leading efforts to analyze, assess, and mitigate national cyber threats

#### **EDUCATION**

Harvard University: Master of Industrial and Organizational Psychology, Dean's List 3.9/4.0

Indiana University: Master of Public Affairs in Finance

Harper College: Post-Bac in Computer Science

Indiana University: Bachelor of Business Management and Public Policy

#### SKILLS

**Program Management:** Program implementation, executive operations, OKRs, KPI development; **Financial Oversight:** Capital and operating budget management, forecasting, cost optimization; **Organizational Capability:** Talent development, succession planning, workforce analytics; **Executive Communications:** Stakeholder engagement, cross-functional collaboration, change management; **HR Technology:** Workday, ServiceNow, HR Analytics, Digital Employee Experience, SaaS, Vendor Management; **Data & Engineering:** Python, SQL, C++, PowerBl, R, Tableau; **Product and Program Lifecycle & Agile:** Al Product Development, Agile, Scrum, Kanban, OKRs, A/B Testing, Go-To-Market Strategy

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

AWS Certified AI Practitioner; AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner; Northwestern Univ. Professional Product Management Certificate; Prosci Change Management; Scrum Alliance Product Owner; Google Analytics